Sara Anne Catherine Whinyates Robertson Letters and Estate Documents LSC.2379
UCLA Library Special Collections
Sara Anne Catherine Whinyates Robertson letters and estate documents
1806-1808
UCLA Library Special Collections
Robertson, Sara Anne Catherine Whinyates
LSC.2379
0.4 linear feet (1 box)
The collection consists of 46 letters, written in India by Sara Anne Catherine Whinyates Robertson. The letters are primarily to her grandmother Lady Frankland, her aunt Harriet Frankland, and her brother Sir Edward Charles Whinyates. The letters describe social life and conditions in British Colonial India. In addition, there are two documents concerning her father's estate in India. The materials date from 1806 to 1808.
The letters are generally in very good, clean, and legible condition, with some minor tears, and loss along folds.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9990846353606533
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Michael Brown Rare Books, LLC from the Manuscript Funds, 2019.
Biographical History
Against her family's wishes, Sara Anne Catherine Whinyates married Lieutenant James Robertson of the Bengal Engineers in 1803. Her grandmother, Lady Frankland, her Aunt Harriet, and her brother Edward Charles were the only family that supported her and wrote to her. Sara and her husband initially resided at Fort William. Situated on the eastern banks of the River Hooghly, the major distributary of the River Ganges, Fort William was an important stronghold and the major trading hub for the East India Company. From the time of their marriage until 1805, British and Indian soldiers clashed in the Second Anglo-Maratha War – Britain's sixth conflict with India since 1766. British forces managed to maintain control of Fort William, but, by 1806, the region still experienced some violence.
Source: Michael Brown Rare Books, LLC. Invoice correspondence, November 15, 2019.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of 46 letters, written in India by Sara Anne Catherine Whinyates Robertson. The letters are written to Robertson's grandmother Lady Frankland; her Aunt Harriet; her brother Sir Edward Charles Whinyates, British Army general, veteran of Waterloo; her uncle William Frankland; and her sisters Amy, Rachel, and Bella. In addition, there are two documents regarding her father's estate in India.
The letters describe social life and conditions in British Colonial India. The letters chronicle when Sara's parents die in Allahabad, India and leave behind two younger orphaned sisters and many debts. Sara sends her two younger sisters home to England so that they may be educated. The Robertsons are transferred from Calcutta to Allahabad after Mr. Robertson is promoted to Chief Engineer at that post. Mr. Robertson is sent into the field several times during various uprisings and insurgencies. Sara desired bringing her older sisters to India so they could "marry well" and be "settled."
Source: Michael Brown Rare Books, LLC. Invoice correspondence, November 15, 2019.
Custodial History
Collection acquired by dealer at an auction in 2017.
British -- India -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Letters (Correspondence).; Robertson, Sara Anne Catherine Whinyates -- Correspondence
- Letter to Harriet Frankland, 1806 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letter to Harriet Frankland, 1806 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter to William Frankland, 1806 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter to Edward Charles Whinyates, 1806 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letter to Amy, 1806 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Documents regarding estate, 1806 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 July 14 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letter to Harriet Frankland, 1806 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 September 11 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 September 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Letter to Rachel Whinyates, 1806 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Letter to Edward Charles Whinyates, 1806 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1806 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Letter to Harriet Frankland, 1806 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Letter to Edward Charles Whinyates, 1806 December 20 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- List of clothes, 1806 August (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Letter to Edward Charles Whinyates, 1807 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Letter to Harriet Frankland, 1807 February (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1807 February 13 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1807 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1807 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Letter to Harriet Frankland, 1807 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Letter to Edward Charles Whinyates, 1807 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Letter to Harriet Frankland, 1807 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Letter to Edward Charles Whinyates, 1807 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1807 August 3 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1807 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1808 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1808 January 24 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1808 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Letter to Edward Charles Whinyates, 1808 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1808 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Letter to Harriet Frankland, 1808 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1808 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Letter to Harriet Frankland, 1808 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1808 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Letter to Edward Charles Whinyates, 1808 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Letter to William Frankland, 1808 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1808 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Letter to Lady Frankland, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 48)